בוקר
טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is מ"א Mem Alef Sanhedrin 41,
we pick up six lines from the bottom on מ' עמוד ב'.
Mem Amud Bet. The next stage of the משנה, Mishnah, beginning of
the line, מכירים אתם אותו. Makirim atem oto. One of the questions
we ask the witnesses is: Do you recognize who the person was?
So you can, you know, sort of like the lineup, do you
know exactly that this is the person who'd committed the crime? So
תנו רבנן, Tana rabanan, our rabbis taught and a ברייתא baraita expands
on the questions that were asked: מכירים אתם אותו, Makirim atem oto,
do you recognize him? נכרי הרג ישראל הרג? Nochri harag Yisrael harag?
If he killed somebody, do you know whether it was a Jew
or non-Jew? You saw him kill somebody, but only when a Jew
kills another Jew is it actually the death penalty. התרתם בו, Hitretem
bo, did you give him התראה? hatra'ah? You know, we know that
you have to give a warning before somebody can be found guilty
or punished in the court. You're not allowed to do that and
if you do that you will receive, you know, the death penalty.
So that was in the משנה, Mishnah, the question about התראה, hatra'ah,
but now in this ברייתא baraita we actually are going to learn
other important requirements that also that make it very hard for a
person to ever be convicted. קיבל עליו התראה: Kibel alav hatra'ah: It's
not enough that you warned him, he has to say, "Yes, I
know that and I don't care and I'm going to do it
anyway." So can you testify to that? התיר עצמו למיתה: Hitir atzmo
lemitah: Did he permit himself, like, open himself up to be executed?
You basically, as we'll see the גמרא Gemara explains this, you know,
you basically have to not only say, "I know that it is
forbidden," but "I know it is forbidden and I am deserving the
death penalty." That idea that התיר עצמו למיתה, Hitir atzmo lemitah, that
basically he accepts upon himself the consequence of the punishment. We'll see
about that in the גמרא, Gemara, but to some degree that's, you
know, addressing the question about what by what right the court has
to do violence against another person and to impose this punishment. Well,
he accepted it, willingly accepted it upon himself. Okay, so המית בתוך
כדי דיבור: Hemit b'toch k'dei dibur: Now, even if he does all
of that, he now has to actually do the crime within תוך
כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibur, within like three seconds of saying, "Yes,
I accept it upon myself," because if not, then we're afraid maybe
he forgot. Now that seems a little absurd, you know, what does
that mean maybe he forgot? Really, like three seconds, that's how long
it takes you to forget?
But maybe a better way of understanding it is is that then
it means that the sin is not done in the context of
the total defiance and of the התיר עצמו למיתה, Hitir atzmo lemitah,
so it does not again give you the license then to to
execute. But okay, it needs to be תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei
dibur. העובד עבודה זרה: Ha'oved avodah zarah: Now let's say that was
a case of murder; let's say somebody is being found guilty for
idolatry. את מי עבד לפעור עבד למרקוליס עבד: Et mi avad l'pe'or
avad l'markolis avad: Do you know which עבודה זרה avodah zarah he
worshiped? Now, as opposed to the ישראל Yisrael and the נכרי Nochri
case, that's not really relevant; each one is punishable by death. But
it is relevant to determine whether the עבודה avodah that was done
is the עבודה avodah that is normal for that god; that would
determine, that's necessary in knowing that he's חייב מיתה. chayav mitha. ובמה
עבד: U'vameh avad: How did he do the עבודה? avodah? בזיבוח בקיטור
בניסוך בהשתחויה? B'zibuach b'kitur b'nisuch b'hishtachavayah? Was it
with slaughtering an animal, burning incense, pouring wine, prostrating? Now all of
those are standard forms of of worship, and regardless of what is
the specific particular form of worship of of this god, when anybody
does any of the generic standard forms of worship, whether it's particular
to the god or whether it's even appropriate for this god is
not relevant, you're always חייב chayav that would for עבודה זרה avodah
zarah when you do one of those forms. So again, this is
not necessary information to make it possible to kill the person, but
this is part of the חקירות chakirot of just trying to ask
many questions and establish all the facts. Also possibly to trip them
up or that they would, you know, maybe they'll contradict one another,
obviously that could be part of the motivation. Okay, so אמר עולא:
Amar Ulla:
Now that's the end of the ברייתא. baraita. Says עולא: Ulla: מניין
להתרעה מן התורה? Minayin le'hatra'ah min haTorah? So he's now introduced this
important idea that you need התראה. hatra'ah. Where do you get this
from in from the תורה? Torah? שנאמר: Shene'emar: ואיש אשר יקח את
אחותו בת אביו או בת אמו V'ish asher yikach et achoto bat
aviv o vat imo וראה את ערותה. v'ra'ah et ervatah. If a
man takes his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter
of his mother, and sees her nakedness. So that is the sin
of, you know, sleeping with a brother, sleeping with a sister, which
is punishable by כרת. karet. So the גמרא Gemara says: אטו בראייה
תליא מילתא? Atu b're'iyah talya miltah? So what do you mean, "sees
the nakedness"? It's not about seeing, it's about the act of of
sex, of intercourse. אלא עד שיראה ראייתו של דבר: Ela ad she'yireh
re'iyuto shel davar:
It tells you that you have to see the ערוה ervah in
the sense of it has to be blatant what is wrong and
the sin has to be blatant before and only in that case
is a person going to be punished.
So only if he know, for example, in this case, that she
is an ערוה, ervah, he sees that fact, then would he be
punished. Now אם אינו עניין לכרת: Im eino inyan l'karet: Now that's
not needed to tell you the divine punishment of כרת, karet, because
God knows whether you're intentional or not intentional and this whole idea
of התראה, hatra'ah, whether it's to establish מזיד meizid or, you know,
again establish a certain degree of defiance and so on, that's only
necessary for a court-imposed punishment. So from this idea of ראה, ra'ah,
it has to be you have to see what you're doing and
know what you're doing is wrong, but that's not needed really to
tell you for this case itself. So top of מ"א עמוד א'.
Mem Alef Amud Alef. תניא עניין למלקות. Tanya inyan lemalkos. So the
court-imposed punishment for כרת karet is lashes. If he's told if you
do this you will be חייב מלקות, chayav malkos, so then the
court can give him lashes, so for that, for that it would
be necessary. So now we know that at least for lashes, to
get lashes you need התראה. hatra'ah. דבי חזקיה תנא, Debei Chizkiya tana,
now
the house of חזקיה Chizkiya teaches, וכי יזיד איש על רעהו להרגו
בערמה, vechi yazid ish al re'ehu lehargo be'arma, not a case of
מלקות, malkos, a case of מיתה misa of execution if a for
murder, if a court, if a man, you know, acts willfully against
his friend to kill him by lying in wait, שהתרו בו ועדיין
הוא מזיד. shehitru bo ve-adayin hu mezid. So it's כי יזיד איש,
ki yazid ish, so that tells you that how do you know
that it is מזיד? meizid? It sounds like in the act of
להרגו בערמה, lehargo be'arma, the killing, it is the fact that he
is מזיד meizid is blatant. Okay, so
that's one way of understanding. The other רש"י Rashi says is that
וכי יזיד vechi yazid
somehow suggests a sense of that it's ongoing. It doesn't say אם
יזיד איש im yazid ish but וכי יזיד vechi yazid sounds like
the מזיד meizid dimension is very present in the act. Okay, so
that shows you that it has to be blatant, that מזיד meizid
dimension. That again by the way might point more to sort of
something being explicit, blatant, and so on, not just trying to get
at what his intent was. Okay, that's another learning and that's from
murder and execution, capital punishment. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, Debei Rabi Yishmael
tana, in the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael they teach, המוצאים
אותו מקושש עצים, hamotzim oto mekoshish etzim, this is by the מקושש,
mekoshish, those who found him מקושש עצים, mekoshish etzim, שהתרו בו ועדיין
הוא מקושש. shehitru bo ve-adayin hu mekoshish. So the idea of מקושש
mekoshish in the process of. It's not מוצאים אותו motzim oto that
he was that he had been מקושש עצים. mekoshish etzim. Even when
they found him, he was still being מקושש עצים. mekoshish etzim. So
that like the sense again of defiance and doing it even in
the presence of the witnesses. שהתרו בו ועדיין הוא מקושש. shehitru bo
ve-adayin hu mekoshish. דבי רבי תנא, Debei Rabi tana, in the house
of רבי Rabi they taught, על דבר אשר ענה את אשת רעהו,
al devar asher ina et eshet re'ehu, on the fact that he
had oppressed or like raped his, you know, a man's wife, so
על עסקי דיבור. al iskei dibbur. So it's על דבר, al devar,
not על אשר ענה. al asher ina. So there has to be
some element of speech that is accompanying, you know, from the witnesses
that is accompanying this act. Okay, so it's clear that some of
these are not necessarily pointing just to the idea of determining his
state of mind. וצריכא, Utzricha, now you need these פסוקים psukim from
all of these different cases. Why? אי כתב רחמנא אחותו, Ie kasav
rachmana achoso, had it just been in the case of the sister,
הוה אמינא hava amina חייב מלקות אין חייב מיתות לא. chayav malkos
in chayav misas lo. Maybe that's only by lashes, you know, that's
a lighter infraction, so we'll only punish if it was with this
explicit defiance. But maybe מיתה misa which is a greater sin, you
know, maybe that we want to punish it even you know even
if there isn't this defiance. I mean you could have gone the
other way, that if it's such a harsher thing we want to
have more safeguards against doing it. But okay. כתב רחמנא וכי יזיד.
Kasav rachmana vechi yazid.
So there it says וכי יזיד. vechi yazid. אי כתב רחמנא וכי
יזיד, Ie kasav rachmana vechi yazid, had it just said that, הוה
אמינא hava amina הני מילי סייף, hani mili sayif, to kill, fine,
that's
רציחה retzicha which is punished by the סייף, sayif, that's considered a
lesser form of execution. אבל סקילה דחמירא, Aval skila dechamira, when it
comes to סקילה skila which is the heaviest form of execution, and
therefore in some ways it's the severest sin, so אימא לא. eima
lo. Maybe you don't need התראה. hatra'ah. Now again you could go
both ways. It's such a terrible sin that we should punish you
even without התראה, hatra'ah, or it's such a weighty punishment that we
want to be you know demand before we do it know that
there is התראה. hatra'ah. But anyway that's why the גמרא Gemara is
saying you needed all of them. Okay. אימא לא צריכא. Eima lo
tzericha. ותרתי בסקילה למה לי? Vetarti binskila lamah li? Now why do
you need two things about סקילה? skila? Because the case of חילול
שבת chillul Shabbos is סקילה skila and the case of על אשר
ענה את אשת רעהו al asher ina et eshet re'ehu
is also the case of סקילה. skila. So why do you need
both? לרבי שמעון לאתויי נשרפין. Lerabi Shimon lasuyei nisrafin. So for רבי
שמעון Rabi Shimon who says that שריפה sreifa is the weightiest, so
you don't know yet to apply it to the absolute weightiest execution
of שריפה. sreifa. So there the extra סקילה skila example tells you
to apply it to that. ולרבנן, Lerabbanan, and for the Rabbis, also
it would tell you because of נשרפין, nisrafin, but מילתא דאתיא בקל
וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא. milsa de'asya bikal vachomer tarch va-kasav lah
kra. Even though once it told you סקילה skila you could have
applied it to the weaker cases, but nevertheless even something that's learned
out from a קל וחומר kal vachomer sometimes you have an extra
פסוק pasuk to include it. ולכתוב רחמנא בסקילה ולייתי הני וליגמר מיניה?
Velichsav rachmana binskila velesei hani veligmar mineih?
So okay, now the גמרא Gemara says I don't understand why did
you need everything before סקילה? skila? Why did you need מלקות? malkos?
You know why did you need סייף? sayif? Just say סקילה skila
and learn everything from it? Again so I would have said as
I said that maybe it's the opposite, maybe something that's heavier you
דוקא dafka need התראה, hatra'ah, something lighter you don't. But the גמרא
Gemara is working with the assumption no, that the heavier it is
the more I might have been prepared to say don't need התראה.
hatra'ah. So if you need it by סקילה skila why do you
need to say everything else? So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי
מילתא דאתיא בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא. hacha nami milsa de-asya
bikal vachomer tarch va-kasav lah kra. You're right, you really don't need
it. It could have just said it by סקילה, skila, but even
though you could have learned out everything from סקילה, skila, the פסוקים
psukim say it by all the lesser forms of punishment as well.
Okay, so that's the פסוקים psukim and again, whatever the פסוקים psukim
are, what's important I think is that some of them sort of
speak towards especially על דבר דיבור, al devar dibbur, you know, that
עדיין הוא מקושש, adayin hu mekoshaysh, there's some sense there also of
defiance, not just about willful intent. התרה עצמו למיתה. hitra atzmo lemita.
Now we get the other idea that's not in the משנה, mishna,
it's not enough that he's warned and he accepts, yes, I know
and I'm doing it anyway, he has to actually accept upon himself
the punishment and I know that I am going to be punished
by you know by execution. מנלן, minalan, where do you know that
you need that? By the way, the גמרא Gemara skipped over how
do you know that you need קיבל על עצמו kibel al atzmo
but supposedly you know that's just necessary. You know that it was
heard and received or else you know he can always claim he
didn't hear it. So מנלן, minalan, how do you know he has
to be התרה עצמו למיתה? hitra atzmo lemita?
So אמר רבא amar Rava says רבא, Rava, first wide line, ואי
תימא חזקיה אמר קרא, ve'isayma Chizkiyah amar kra, יומת המת, yumat hamet,
you know, so it says "on the word of two witnesses will
the dead person you know will the dead be put to death."
עד שיתיר עצמו למיתה, ad sheyatir atzmo lemita, he also already has
to be המת, hamet, the dead person, you know and you know
and he has to make himself already the dead, the walking dead.
So and then you can put him to death. So again I
think that this idea is not just about degree of מזיד meizid
and you've accepted the consequences like informed action, but also to some
degree gives a license to בית דין. beis din. You have already
made yourself a מת, met, we are just actualizing that. אמר רב
חנן, amar Rav Chanan, עדי נערה המאורסה שהוזמו אין נהרגין. edei naara
hameurasa shehuzmu ein neheragin. So now this is a statement not really
about our issue about התראה hatra'a but we'll see how we will
circle it back to that. If witnesses come and say that this
you know woman, this נערה na'ara young girl who was מאורסה meurasa
and then she went committed adultery, she was married, committed adultery and
then they become found to be עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, so even
though the act of adultery is punished by death and כאשר זמם
kaasher zamam you would think you would put them to death, he
teaches, רב חנן Rav Chanan teaches, אין נהרגין, ein neheragin, they don't
get put to death. Why not? מתוך שיכולים לומר לאוסרה על בעלה
באנו mitoch sheyecholim lomar leosra al baala banu because since עדים זוממים
edim zomemim is I you know what they were זומם zomem אשר
זמם לעשות לרעהו, asher zamam laasos lere'eiho, so the question is what
were they really trying to accomplish? You know and by עדים זוממים
edim zomemim you don't use the principle sort of like in פסיק
רישא psik reisha and it doesn't matter what you know you were
only trying to do one thing. If the you know they could
say, so I'm sorry I ran ahead, so the basic point here
is they could say "yes we said that she committed adultery but
our only point, we weren't thinking about the fact that she would
get put to death. The only point we were trying to achieve
was to make her forbidden to her husband." So again that seems
to be the fact that עדים זוממים edim zomemim can make that
claim seems to be based on the idea of אשר זמם asher
zamam and you know that it's what they were trying to do.
It still is pretty ironic because especially as we've been seeing you
know the court will will certainly you know warn them and and
you know cross-examine them and it'll be very very clear that the
consequence of their testimony is that she's going to be put to
death. So and nevertheless they can claim "but that wasn't our point,
that wasn't why we came to testify and therefore that's not כאשר
זמם." kaasher zamam. So they actually escape that punishment. So that's a
big חידוש, chiddush, but let's see also how the גמרא Gemara makes
it relevant to our discussion. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
and the גמרא Gemara says like just lost place.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this, והא אתרו בה, veha
asru bah,
so it says so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, but when
you actually you know for רב חנן Rav Chanan to be a
חידוש chiddush it has to be that she was going to get
put to death. The only way she was going to get put
to death on their testimony is if they testified that they gave
her התראה. hatra'a. So if they're testifying that they gave her התראה
hatra'a warning, clearly the only reason to say that is to get
her put to death. So how can they claim if התראה hatra'a
is needed, how can they ever claim we weren't trying to get
her put to death? Excellent question. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. דלא אתרו בה, dilo asru bah, okay no they say
they didn't warn her. So then what's the חידוש chiddush of רב
חנן? Rav Chanan? ואי לא אתרו בה היכי מקטלה? ve'i lo asru
bah heichi mikatla? So then how could she ever get killed? So
obviously רב חנן Rav Chanan isn't teaching us anything. So the גמרא
Gemara says באשה חבירה, be'isha chavera, we're talking about a woman who's
a חבירה, chavera, okay, that she is a you know חבירה chavera
is people that were very careful on תרומות ומעשרות trumos umaasros and
טומאה וטהרה, tuma vetahara, generally like a you know an educated informed
person. And normally the הלכה halacha is there's an opinion as the
גמרא Gemara will say ואליבא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה vealiba d'Rabbi Yosi
bar Rabbi Yehuda and according following רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yosi
bar Rabbi Yehuda's teaching דתניא detanya we learned in a ברייתא. braisa.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר חבר אין צריך התראה. Rabbi Yosi bar
Rabbi Yehuda omer chaver ein tzarich hatra'a. By when it's somebody who's
like a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, somebody who knows הלכה, halacha, they
don't require התראה hatra'a and they can be put to death even
without it. Why? לפי שלא ניתנה התראה אלא להבחין בין שוגג למזיד
lefi shelo nitna hatra'a ela lehavchin bein shogeg lemeizid for the only
purpose of התראה hatra'a is to distinguish between whether you're שוגג shogeg
or מזיד meizid and somebody who knows הלכה halacha obviously they know
what they're doing and obviously they're מזיד. meizid. So How, that's really
important חידוש, Chiddush, because it seemed until now that התראה Hatra'ah was
a formal part of the process. Not only is he not saying
that it's not a formal part of the process, he's actually saying
that its whole purpose was to get to state of mind. And
one of the things we had been talking about
was, not really, some of this might be to be doing it
in a context of defiance, some of this might be doing to
be doing it as accepting the penalty upon yourself. But he is
saying no, only purpose of התראה Hatra'ah is to get to state
of mind. תוספות Tosafos says that according to him, you don't need
התרה עצמו למיתה, Hiter atzmo loso miso, which is clearly not just
about the מזיד Mezid component. Fine. So if you are following this
approach, then it's possible that they could that this would be a
woman that knew הלכה Halacha and that she could be put to
death without התראה, Hatra'ah, and that's how they could say we weren't
trying to put her to death. Okay? Okay, so that's what's really
interesting here is these different approach to what the purpose of התראה
Hatra'ah is. So let the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. וכיון דאינהו לא מיקטלי אי היכי מיקטלא הויא לה עדות שאתה
יכול להזימה. V'kivan d'inu lo mikitli, i heichi mikitla, havya lah eidus
she-at yachol l'hazimah. So the Gemara says, wait a minute, if that's
true, if רב חנן Rav Chanan's teaching is true, now we're no
longer about התראה. Hatra'ah. If רב חנן Rav Chanan's teaching is true,
when witnesses come and say this woman who was a, knows הלכה
Halacha or married to a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham so we assume
she knows הלכה, Halacha, it's interesting how we understand what אשה חבירה
Isha Chaveira means, anyway, this woman, whatever, she's a married woman, she
committed
adultery, and and רב חנן Rav Chanan is saying, oh, we're not
going to put the עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim to death because they
could say לאוסרה אבעלה. L'osra a'baalah. But he means, but what's implicit
is if they hadn't been found זוממים, Zomemim, she would have been
put to death. But how can you put her to death on
their testimony if they could never be put to death if they're
found to be זוממים? Zomemim? The principle is that a testimony that
cannot turn them into זוממים Zomemim is not accepted. So if רב
חנן Rav Chanan is right that without התראה Hatra'ah in אשה חבירה,
Isha Chaveira, they'll never be put to death if found זוממים, Zomemim,
then then how could he be implying that if they hadn't been
found זוממים, Zomemim, she would have been executed? It's עדות שאתה יכול
להזימה. Eidus she-at yachol l'hazimah. Testimony that can never be made זוממים.
Zomemim. וכל עדות שאתה יכול להזימה לא שמה עדות. V'chol eidus she-at
yachol l'hazimah lo shmah eidus. So the Gemara says, הכי נמי קאמר.
Hachi nami ka'amar. Okay, that was his point. His point was, מתוך
שאין נהרגים, Mitoch she-ein neheragim, in a case where witnesses come and
say this אשה אשה חבירה Isha Isha Chaveira committed adultery, since they
would never be killed because they could always just say לאוסרה אבעלה
באנו L'osra a'baalah banu if they didn't say that they gave her
התראה. Hatra'ah. So once you start with that point that they won't
be killed, מתוך שאין נהרגים שיכולים לומר לאוסרה אבעלה באנו, Mitoch she-ein
neheragim she-yecholim l'omar l'osra a'baalah banu, אף היא אינה נהרגת. Af hi
einah neherageth. So yes, רב חנן Rav Chanan had that was my
point. First you start with the idea that they can't be זוממים
Zomemim and be executed, and once you say that, then she also
can't be executed. Okay, very nice. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
דהויא לה עדות שאתה יכול להזימה. D'havya lah eidus she-at yachol l'hazimah.
Okay,
fine. אלא באשה חבירה דקיימא
לן דמיקטלא לליבא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה היכי משכחת לה? Ella b'isha
chaveira d'kaiman lan d'mikitla l'iba d'rabbi yose b'rabbi yehuda heichi mishkachat lah?
So the Gemara says, okay, then I got a question according to
רב חנן. Rav Chanan. We just said that if a woman is
a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham or knows הלכה Halacha or married to
a תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, that she can be executed even without
התראה Hatra'ah for committing adultery. That's basically what רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda said. Now, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda didn't exactly say it specifically by a case of a
woman, but okay, he did it by a חבר. Chaver. But the
Gemara says we have always assumed that for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
this would apply to a case of a woman who is a
חבירה Chaveira who committed adultery. So according to him, how can that
woman ever be put to death if what רב חנן Rav Chanan
is saying is true? So let's see what the Gemara says. היכי
משכחת לה? Heichi mishkachat lah? So now you could have said by
the way that you could be case where she, even though she
was an אשה חבירה, Isha Chaveira, the witnesses say they warned her.
But again, the point of the Gemara is that we have always
always understood רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's teaching that an אשה חבירה Isha
Chaveira who commits adultery, even without warning, will be put to death.
So how can that be possible if what רב חנן Rav Chanan
is saying is correct? So the Gemara says, כשזינתה וחזרה וזינתה. Keshe-zintha
v'chazra v'zintha.
Okay, it would be a case that they testify that she committed
adultery twice. So the only reason for the second testimony is not
to make her forbidden on her husband, she's already forbidden on her
husband. So that second testimony could only be have the effect of
getting her killed. Because she's already forbidden on her husband. כשזינתה וחזרה
וזינתה. Keshe-zintha v'chazra v'zintha. So the Gemara says, והא יכול לומר לאוסרה
אבועל השני באנו? V'ha yachol l'omar l'osra a'boal hasheini banu? Okay,
but one minute, says the Gemara, maybe it wasn't to get her
killed, maybe it was to make her forbidden to her second lover,
assuming it was a different man, because a woman who commits adultery
is forbidden to her husband and the man that she committed adultery
with. So again, even if she did it twice, maybe it was
not about getting her executed. So the Gemara says, לאוסרה אבועל השני
באנו, L'osra a'boal hasheini banu, כשזינתה מבועל ראשון. Keshe-zintha miboal rishon. Oh,
no,
they testify that she had sex with the same man twice. Okay,
and therefore the only purpose of the second testimony can't be now
to make... forbidden on
her
relative, and
again, we have to be twice. The first time it makes her
forbidden on her husband, she had sex, okay, but now the second
time it was with a relative, so it can't be to make
her forbidden on her relative, she's like a brother, she's already forbidden
on a relative, so it's only to get her executed. Okay. So
that's how that works. מאי שנא נערה מאורסה דנקט אפילו נשואה נמי.
mai shena na'ara me'orasa de-nakat afilu nesua nami. Okay,
so that was how we have this idea that a big חידוש
chidush that עדים זוממים edim zomemim can say, oh no, we weren't
thinking about that, and that gets them off the hook. Okay, and
then that means that it becomes עדות שיכול להזימה. edus she-yachol lehazima.
Okay, that's one point. The other point is this really important point
about a חבר chaver and a חבירה chavera that they don't, according
to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose at least, they don't need התראה. hatra'ah.
So now the גמרא Gemara is saying then just wants to one
thing we want, now that we've figured out like the scenarios here,
one thing we want to figure out: why did רב חננא Rav
Chanana give us the example of a נערה מאורסה? na'ara me'orasa? I
mean, I've been describing it now like a woman commits adultery, like
why specifically נערה מאורסה? na'ara me'orasa?
So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי שנא נערה מאורסה דנקט אפילו נשואה
נמי, mai shena na'ara me'orasa de-nakat afilu nesua nami, even if it
was a נשואה nesua and even not a נערה. na'ara. אין אין
אלא, in ein ela,
yes that's correct, אלא אפילו האי דלא יתבה תותיה יכולים לומר לאוסרה
בבעל באנו. ela afilu hai delo yasva tusei yacholim lomar la'osvah ba'al
banu. But the גמרא, Gemara,
there's a חידוש. chidush. Even this young woman who never actually started
sleeping with her husband and she only was an ארוסה, arusa, you
know, and then you could say like how could, maybe they're obviously
not coming to make her forbidden to her husband, that's not even
on the table yet that she and her husband are having sex,
nevertheless, it still they could still make that claim. Okay. Fine. Now,
so that's the end of that whole discussion, which was really brought
in because of, you know, it was highly interesting, but it was
the key thing relevant to us was this principle of רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose of לא ניתנה התראה אלא להפריש בין שוגג למזיד. lo
nitna hatra'ah ela lehafrish bein shogeg le-mezid. All right. אמר רב חסדא:
amar Rav Chisda: אחד אומר בסייף הרגו ואחד אומר בארירין הרגו, echad
omer be-sayif harago ve-echad omer be-aririn harago,
one person says that he was killed with a sword and the
other says it was killed with ארירין, aririn, which you know, is
questioning exactly what that means. Anyway, one says it's sort of like
an awl, like a type of a, you know, a poker or
something like that. אין זה נכון. ein zeh nachon.
So that's not, he's quoting the פסוק: pasuk: והנה אמת נכון הדבר.
vehineh emet nachon ha-davar.
So it's not נכון, nachon, it's not מכוון, mechuvun, the עדות, edus,
the testimonies are not aligned and, you know, they are contradicting one
another in the בדיקות bedikot and you would throw it out. Okay,
that's what we learned in the משנה. Mishnah. You know, the משנה
Mishnah said if one of them says "I don't know" by the
בדיקות, bedikot, the testimony is good, but if they contradict one another
in the בדיקות, bedikot, then it gets thrown out. So that's not
the חידוש, chidush, the חידוש chidush is the next line. אחד אומר
כלים שחורים ואחד אומר כלים לבנים הרי זה נכון. echad omer kelim
shechorim ve-echad omer kelim levanim harei zeh nachon.
If they're contradicting one another in the בדיקות bedikot that are not
directly about the act—he was wearing white clothes, no he was wearing
black clothes—then that is considered secondary or, you know, marginal, not central
and therefore that is not considered that their testimony doesn't align. They
didn't say the exact same thing. You know, eyewitness testimony is highly,
it's highly like not reliable. I mean, it's funny that in הלכה
halacha it's all about the testimony of witnesses, but okay, you don't
see the exact same things, that's like marginal, that's the noise, but
as long as their testifying is aligned with the basic definition of
the act of the sin. Okay, even though it wasn't essential, it
doesn't, you know, as a matter of הלכה halacha was it this
or the other thing? But,
but nevertheless, they have to be aligned when they're describing the actual
act of the sin. Okay. מתיבי, meitivei, says the גמרא, Gemara, I'll
challenge this. נכון, nachon, as the פסוק pasuk says that it is
correct, שיהא נכון, she-yehe nachon, that they have to be aligned. Okay.
אחד אומר בסייף הרגו ואחד אומר בארירין הרגו אחד אומר כלים שחורים
ואחד אומר כלים לבנים אין זה נכון.
echad omer be-sayif harago ve-echad
omer be-aririn harago echad omer kelim shechorim ve-echad omer kelim levanim ein
zeh nachon.
So here you have a ברייתא braita that teaches explicitly against it,
that says even if they're just disagreeing not only on the murder
weapon but also on what he was wearing, it is not aligned
and you throw it out. So the גמרא Gemara says, תרגמה רב
חסדא בסודר שחנקו בו. tirgema Rav Chisda be-sudar she-chanku bo. So this
is such a weak answer, the גמרא Gemara says: no, it doesn't
mean what clothes he was wearing, it means that he committed murder
through strangulating the person using his clothes, using his own handkerchief and
they're debating the color of the handkerchief that was used to strangle.
Okay, obviously does not sound like that at all. דהיינו סייף ארירין,
de-hainu sayif aririn, which is the same type of question about the
sword or the awl. Even here you could have said, look, they're
agreeing on the murder weapon, they're just disagreeing on the color, but
once it's about the act itself then that is enough to make
it not consistent and throw it out.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. אחד אומר סנדלו שחורים ואחד
אומר סנדלו לבנים אין זה נכון. echad omer sandalo shechorim ve-echad omer
sandalo levanim ein zeh nachon.
Another ברייתא braita that they've disagreed the color of the shoes says
you throw it out. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם נמי כגון
שבעט בו בסנדלו והרגו. hatam nami kegon she-ba'at bo be-sandalo ve-harago. Oh,
so the shoe was the murder weapon. He kicked him with his
shoe and he killed him. Okay, again, not פשט pshat *Pshat*. תא
שמע *Tash ma*, come in here, you know, מעשה *Maaseh*, this goes
back to our משנה *Mishna*, מעשה ובדק בן זכאי באוקצי תאנים *Maaseh
u-vadak Ben Zakkai be-uktzei te'anim*. Ben Zakkai did a check them in
terms of the you know the little twigs of the figs. So
how do you get that? So that seems completely trivial and he
was testing them or checking them because if they were not consistent
he would throw it out. So that's not part of... that wouldn't
be a basis for throwing it out according to you. So אמר
רמי בר חמא כגון דאקטף תאנה בשבת דאלהא קמיקטל *Amar Rami Bar
Chama kagon de-aktaf te'ena be-Shabbat de-alah ka mikital*. So he says, oh
forget it, we're not talking about murder, we're talking that he he
plucked a fig on שבת *Shabbat*. So that is part of the
actual עבירה *aveirah*. So the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says והתניא vehatanya, אמרו
לו תחת תאנה הרגו *ve-hatanya amru lo tachat te'ena harago*? But one
minute, the you know that's not the actual ברייתא braisa, *Baraita*. The
ברייתא braisa *Baraita* says that you know the context is is that
he was killed under a fig tree and they're just debating what
was the thing with the with the twigs of the fig tree.
So it's about a case of murder. So how do you get
this to be part of the act? So אלא ella, אמר רמי
בר חמא כגון ששפטו ביחור של תאנה *ella amar Rami Bar Chama
kagon she-shafto be-yichur shel te'ena*. You know, he speared him with the
little twig of the fig. I don't know how you get that
through somebody's eye, their temple. I don't know how the little twig
on the on the fig is enough to kill anybody but we're
totally doing somersaults in order to make this fit with the teaching
of what do you call it of רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*, even
though the פשט *pshat* of all of this is any contradiction in
the בדיקות bedikos. *bedikot* is a basis for throwing it out. So
now the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says like this, תא שמע *Tash ma*,
come in here. אמר להן תאנה זו עוקציה דקין או עוקציה גסין?
תאנים שחורות, תאנים לבנות? *Amar lahen te'ena zu uktzeiha dakin o uktzeiha
gasin? Te'anim shechorot, te'anim levanot?* That one of the questions that was
asked was not only are the twigs you know thick or thin,
but are the actual figs white or black? So now and the
גמרא *Gemara* is assuming there's no way you can kill somebody, maybe
you can kill them with a little poke in the twig but
there's no way you can kill somebody with the fig itself. So
how can this be central to the act? So the גמרא *Gemara*
says אלא אמר רב יוסף מבי בן זכאי לא תוסיף איניש? *Ella
amar Rav Yosef mibei Ben Zakkai lo tosif inish?* You're going to
ask from בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai*? בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai* was the
one who asked about the figs. שאני בן זכאי דבדיקות כחקירות משוי
להו *Shani
Ben Zakkai de-bedikot ke-chakirot mashvei lehu*. בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai*... made the
חקירות chakiros *chakirot* like the בדיקות bedikos? *bedikot*? No, בדיקות bedikos, כחקירות
משוי להו *bedikot ke-chakirot mashvei lehu*. בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai* made the
בדיקות bedikos, *bedikot* like the חקירות chakiros, *chakirot*. בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai*
said any disagreement about the חקירות chakiros *chakirot* I'm going to throw
it out, so what we're trying to do now is we're trying
to make רב חסדא's *Rav Chisda's* statement a debate of תנאים *Tannaim*.
רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* is saying only a contradiction of בדיקות bedikos
*bedikot* that are central to the act and even though it's clear
that there are תנאים *Tannaim* like all the ברייתות *Baraitot* we quoted
and certainly בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai* that says that even if it's
not central to the act, saying okay that's his that opinion, but
I'm going to claim that the majority opinion is only if they
contradict by the בדיקות bedikos *bedikot* central to the act. Right. So
the גמרא *Gemara* now says like this. By the way, it's not
clear for בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai*, the language of the גמרא *Gemara*
says it makes it like בדיקות bedikos, *bedikot* like חקירות *chakirot*. Would
he throw it out even if somebody said איני יודע *eini yodeia*?
That's not clear. It seems like the... he's consistent with the משנה
*mishna* that איני יודע *eini yodeia* is not a problem. But at
least for the sense of contradiction, any contradiction for בן זכאי *Ben
Zakkai*. But that's just a בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai* position. Okay.
Now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. מן בן זכאי? *Man Ben
Zakkai?* Who is this בן זכאי *Ben Zakkai*? אילימא רבי יוחנן בן
זכאי *Ilima Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai*, if it's the רבי יוחנן בן
זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai* that we all know, then מי הוה
בסנהדרי? *mi hava be-Sanhedri?* How could he have been in the סנהדרין
*Sanhedrin* on a capital case? Why not? ותניא כל שנותיו של רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי מאה ועשרים שנה *Ve-tanya kol shenotav shel Rabbi Yochanan
ben Zakkai me'ah ve-esrim shana*. רבי יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai* lived 120 years. ארבעים שנה עסק בפרקמטיא *Arba'im shana asak be-prakmatya*,
40 years he was in business. מ"ם שנה למד *Mem shana lamad*,
40 years he was learning תורה Torah *Torah*. ארבעים שנה לימד *Arba'im
shana limed*, and for 40 years he taught. So only in his
last 40 years was he at the stage of really being a
major רב *rav* and teaching תורה *Torah* and presumably only at that
last 40 years was he able to be on a בית דין
beis din *Beis Din* and to deal with a case of capital
crime. Okay, why couldn't he? Because ותניא *ve-tanya* we taught in the
ברייתא braisa *Baraita*, ארבעים שנה קודם חורבן הבית churban habayis. גלתה סנהדרין
וישבה לה בחנות *Arba'im shana kodem churban ha-bayit galta Sanhedrin ve-yashva la
be-chanut*. That 40 years before the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* was destroyed,
the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* left the לשכת הגזית lishkas hagazis, *Lishkat HaGazit*, left
its place in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, dwelt in one of
the stores sort of in the in the nearby sort of area,
and and it was not dealing with capital cases. That was 40
years before the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* was destroyed and we of
course know that רבי יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai* survived
the destruction of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So if רבי יוחנן
בן זכאי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai* was beyond the destruction of the
בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* and he was only in a position to
be in the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* in his last 40 years, then he
was never in the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* when it was dealing with capital
cases. Okay, ותניא *ve-tanya*, okay, בחנות *be-chanut*, ואמר רבי יצחק בר אבדימי
לומר שלא דנו דיני קנסות *ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi lomar she-lo
danu dinei knasot*. The reason that they moved was because they it
was not dealing anymore with cases about fines. דיני קנסות סלקא דעתך?
*Dinei knasot salka daitach?* What do you mean fines? Who cares about
fines? You don't need the בית דין הגדול beis din hagadol *Beis
Din HaGadol* sitting in the לשכת הגזית *Lishkat HaGazit* to deal with
cases of קנס *knas*. אלא שלא דנו דיני נפשות *ella she-lo danu
dinei nefashot*. No, it means capital crimes. Okay, because that's a principle
that we have... that you can only do capital crimes if the
בית דין beis din הגדול is sitting in the לשכת הגזית, even
though you don't need a בית דין beis din? הגדול for capital
crimes. ותנן, usnan, and we taught in the mishna, משחרב בית המקדש
התקין רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, mishecharav beis hamikdash hitkin Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was making תקנות takanos after the חורבן
churban, הבית. We know that Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai obviously lived through
the חורבן, so he could not have been on a בית דין
beis din that was dealing with capital crimes, you know, in his
last, you know, when he was able to be on a בית
דין beis din in his last forty years. So אלא בן זכאי
דעלמא, ella Ben Zakkai d'alma, alright, some other Ben Zakkai, maybe it
was his brother, you know, who knows? And that's why he wasn't
given Rabban Yochanan, it was just some, of course why are we
just quoting some random person, but okay. הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami
mistavra, that it also makes sense. דאי סלקא דעתך רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי, de'i salda'atach Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, if it was Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai, קרי ליה רבי בן זכאי? kari leh Rebbi Ben Zakkai?
How could we have called Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai Ben Zakkai? We
should have used his title Rabban. Okay, so clearly we are talking
about not Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. Number one. והתניא, one minute says
the גמרא, we have a ברייתא, מעשה ובדק רבן יוחנן בן זכאי
בעוקצי תאנים. maaseh ubadak Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai be'oktzei te'einim. We have
a ברייתא that explicitly identifies this with Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. So
now we got a problem. Why are we not calling him by
his name and by his title and how could he have been
on a בית דין? beis din, So אלא, so we're gonna have
one answer that answers both. תלמיד היושב לפני רבו הוה, talmid hayoshev
lifnei rabbo hava, this was before he was רבן, Rabban, he had
סמיכה, smicha, before he was in the position of teaching during his
middle forty years, not his last, when the בית דין beis din
was still dealing with capital crimes. So now we got him at
the time the בית דין dealing with capital crimes, he doesn't have
the title רבן, Rabban, but he was sitting there in the presence
of the בית דין, a תלמיד talmid sitting in front of his
רבו. rabbo. ואמר מילתא ומסתבר להו טעמיה, ve'amar milta umistabber lehu ta'ameh,
and he said something and people said oh, that's a good idea,
you know, let's try to check the witnesses on the question about
the figs. Okay, and like we learned before, you know, when even
the student suggests things, normally that's about arguing, you know, about whether
he's innocent or guilty, but people had, you know, the court clerks
and whatever and their students and they would be open to the
input. So he said that and then they adopted that. וקבעוה בשמיה.
ukva'uha bishmeih.
So then when they decided to let's start asking about the figs,
this was taught that it was his idea even though he wasn't
on the בית דין proper during that time. כי הוי לומד בן
זכאי הוי קרי ליה, ki hava lommed Ben Zakkai hava kari leh,
when he was still in the middle forty years and just learning
he was called Ben Zakkai. כתלמיד היושב לפני רבו, ketalmid hayoshev lifnei
rabbo, like because he was a תלמיד, talmid, he wasn't yet had
סמיכה. smicha. כי הוי מלמד ורבן יוחנן בן זכאי הוי קרי ליה,
ki hava melammed veRabban Yochanan ben Zakkai hava kari leh,
then when he was teaching and had סמיכה, smicha, then he was
called by his title. כי קרי ליה בן זכאי, ki kari leh
Ben Zakkai, now when the mishna calls him Ben Zakkai taught that
you should ask about the figs, so על שם דמעיקרא, al shem
deme'ikkara, that's because when he actually made that suggestion, that was his
name Ben Zakkai. וכי קרי ליה רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, vechi kari
leh Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, when the ברייתא refers to him as
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai asked about the figs, על שם דהשתא, al
shem de'hashta,
that was because that was the name he had when the mishna
was being written, at that stage he was always Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai. Okay, that was an elegant solution. Alright, now let's keep on
going, so that's about contradicting by the בדיקות. ומעשה ובדק, umaaseh ubadak,
okay, מה בין חקירות? mah bein chakiros?
What is the difference between חקירות and בדיקות? So this is the
difference about whether you can get away with saying I don't know.
So let's take a look. So
and the mishna says not only if one of the witnesses say
I don't know about the בדיקות, but even if both of them
say I don't know by the בדיקות, it's still okay. Now presumably
by the way, that means the non-central בדיקות as opposed to the
central ones, but again that depends on how you understand what the
context of was when they were contradicted that it was a problem.
But okay. Anyway, the mishna says if they say I don't know
by the בדיקות it's okay. So let's see, מאי אפילו שנים אומרים?
mai afilu shenayim omerim? Why does it say even if two say?
פשיטא, pishita, obviously, כי אמר אחד איני יודע עדותן קיימת, ki amar
echad eini yodea edutan kayyamet, if one of them says I don't
know it's still good. כי אמרו בי תרי נמי עדותן קיימת, ki
amru be trei nami edutan kayyamet, obviously then you don't have two
witnesses on that point. So if one person's I don't know works
then if both of them say I don't know it also works,
there's no חידוש chiddush there.
So אמר רב ששת הרישא קאי, amar Rav Sheshet hareisha ka'ei, it's
really not going on the case of I don't know and on
the בדיקות, it's really going on the earlier part of the mishna.
והכי קאמר, vehachi ka'amar, בחקירות, bachakiros, totally changing the text, when it
comes to בחקירות bachakiros about the time and location, אפילו שנים אומרים
ידענו, afilu shenayim omerim yadanu, even if two, if three witnesses and
two say we know, ואחד אומר איני יודע, ve'echad omer eini yodea,
and one says I don't know, עדותן בטילה. edutan beteila. Okay now,
completely changing the text, making it go on the חקירות, making it
two are saying not I don't know but the two are saying
I do know and one is saying I don't know. Okay fine.
Obviously not the פשט of the mishna but that's how he's reading
it. But bottom line is though he's teaching that when it comes
to the חקירות we are so exacting that even if you have
two witnesses that are that work, if the third one says I
don't know, so since all three of them together form a כת,
kat, then you would basically throw everything out. Okay even though it's
just an I don't know, it's not even a contradiction.
So איני יודע עדותן בטילה. eini yodea edutan beteila. כמאן? keman? Who
is that going
like? asks the גמרא, כרבי. keRebbi. This is
the
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* I'm going to go with תוספות'ס *Tosfos's* approach.
This is the רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that I mean רש"י *Rashi*
says it's talking about a position that you have to make all
three witnesses זוממים *zomemim* and therefore all three
and it sort of becomes like an עדות שאתה יכול להזימה *eidus
she’ata yachol l’hazima* if one says I don't know. But תוספות *Tosfos*
actually says that no, that's not a רבי... I mean רש"י *Rashi*
says that's not really רבי עקיבא'ס *Rabbi Akiva's* position. It's רבי שמעון'ס
*Rabbi Shimon's* one, but תוספות *Tosfos* says about actually the point here
is that רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is the one that says if
one of the witnesses is a קרוב *karov* or פסול *pasul*, then
because they are all three one unit you throw it all out,
and that's the point here. איני יודע *eini yodea* is like being
a פסול *pasul* and you throw it all out. Okay, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this,
where were we? כמאן כרבי עקיבא דמקיש שלשה
לשנים *keman k’Rabbi Akiva
d’makish shlosha lishnayim*. Okay. ואמר רבא *v’amar Rava* says רבא
*Rava*, והא עדות קיימת קתני *v’ha eidus kayemes katani*, but רבא *Rava*
says you can't say that. The משנה *Mishna* says not that you
know you're changing way too many things you make the two not
saying I don't know but two saying I do know and you're
changing where the משנה *Mishna* says that it works to saying that
it doesn't work and you throw it out. So that's too much
violence to the text, you can't get away with that. אלא אמר
רבא *ela amar Rava*, rather says רבא *Rava*, הכי קאמר *hachi ka’amar*,
here's how you have to read even too. אפילו בחקירות שנים אומרים
ידענו ואחד אומר איני יודע *afilu b’chakiros shnayim omrim yadanu v’echad omer
eini yodea*, I'm still going to go with your part of your
reread that the two are not saying
I don't know, they're saying I do know, and that we're talking
about חקירות *chakiros*, and we're all going to make those major changes.
So even if it's a case about time and place and two
say that I do know and one says I don't know, nevertheless
even though one is saying I don't know, אפילו בחקירות שנים אומרים
ידענו ואחד אומר איני יודע עדותן קיימת *afilu b’chakiros shnayim omrim yadanu
v’echad omer eini yodea edutan kayemes*, it does work. So that at
least keeps, even though it completely changes the scenario, it keeps the
end of the משנה *Mishna* where even with two it works. So
even with two saying I do know and one saying I don't
know, and even in a case of חקירות *chakiros*, it's still going
to work, and we don't say throw the whole thing out even
though it's חקירות *chakiros*, כמאן דלא כרבי עקיבא *keman d'lo k'Rabbi Akiva*,
not like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* because for רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
you would throw the whole thing out. Okay, anyway, both of those
are reads that are obviously not at all פשט *pshat* of the
text. רב כהנא ורב ספרא תנו סנהדרין בי רבה *Rav Kahana v’Rav
Safra tanu Sanhedrin bei Rabba*. רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* and רב ספרא
*Rav Safra* were learning סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* in the ישיבה *yeshiva* of רבה
*Rabba*. פגעו ביה ברמי בר חמא *pagu beih b’Rami bar Chama*. רמי
בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* bumped into them on the street. אמר
להו מאי אמריתו בסנהדרין דבי רבה *amar lehu mai amritu b’Sanhedrin d’bei
Rabba*? Oh, I hear you're learning סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, what is it, you
know, like what are you learning in ישיבה *yeshiva*? Tell me a
חידוש *chiddush* that you learned from רבה *Rabba*. אמרו ליה *amru lei*,
they said to him, ומאי אמינא בסנהדרין גרירתא ומאי קשיא לך *u’mai
amina b’Sanhedrin grirata u’mai kashya lach*? And they said to him like
okay, what do you normally say about סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, like you know,
and what's bothering you? Meaning, we could tell you a חידוש *chiddush*
we learned, but obviously you're asking the question because something you have
some question. Tell us what your question is and we'll tell you
if we've heard something relevant.
Okay, so let's see, ומאי קשיא בה *u’mai kashya bah*? So אמר
להו *amar lehu*, he said to them, מהא דקתני מה בין חקירות
לבדיקות *me’ha d’katani mah bein chakiros l’bedikos*. What's our משנה *Mishna*? The
משנה *Mishna* says what's the difference between חקירות *chakiros* and בדיקות *bedikos*?
חקירות אחד אומר איני יודע עדותן בטלה *chakiros echad omer eini yodea
edutan betala*. בדיקות אחד אומר איני יודע ואפילו שנים אומרים אין אנו
יודעים עדותן קיימת *bedikos echad omer eini yodea v’afilu shnayim omrim ein
anu yodeim edutan kayemes*. Exactly this difference about חקירות איני יודע *chakiros
eini yodea* gets thrown out, בדיקות איני יודע *bedikos eini yodea* it
works. So here's my question: מכדי *michdi*, let's take a look. אידי
ואידי דאורייתא *idi v’idi d’oraisa*. בדיקות *bedikos* and חקירות *chakiros* are both
learned from פסוקים *psukim*. היא מה ישנא חקירות ומה ישנא בדיקות *hi
mah yishna chakiros u’mah yishna bedikos*? What's the difference? If by חקירות
איני יודע *chakiros eini yodea* doesn't work, then by בדיקות *bedikos* it
should also not work. Now obviously there's an obvious answer because חקירות
*chakiros* is a problem about הזמה *hazama*, יכול להזימם *yachol l’hazimam*. And
once they're saying איני יודע *eini yodea*, it's אינו יכול להזימם *eino
yachol l’hazimam*. בדיקות
*bedikos* is about נכון *nachon* that it's consistent. So איני יודע *eini
yodea* doesn't make something inconsistent. That's what I would say. Let's see
what they say. Okay. מה ישנא חקירות ומה ישנא בדיקות *mah yishna
chakiros u’mah yishna bedikos*? אמרו ליה *amru lei*, they said to him,
הכי השתא *hachi hashta*? I don't... here, what type of question is
that? בחקירות אחד אומר איני יודע עדותן בטלה דהויא לה עדות שאי
אתה יכול להזימה *b’chakiros echad omer eini yodea edutan betala d’havya lah
eidus she’ei ata yachol l’hazima*. Exactly, look at that, you know exactly
as I was saying because it's what the גמרא *Gemara* says. Okay,
so once they say they don't know, it makes it not possible
to... עדות *eidus* that you can't turn into זוממים *zomemim*, and that's
the reason it's a problem. אתה יכול להזימם *ata yachol l’hazimam*. בדיקות
אמרו ליה אחד מהן איני יודע עדותן קיימת עדות שאתה יכול להזימה
להו *bedikos amru lei echad mehen eini yodea edutan kayemes eidus she’ata
yachol l’hazima lehu*. But by בדיקות *bedikos*, saying איני יודע *eini yodea*,
it's still an עדות *eidus* that could become זוממים *zomemim*, so therefore
saying איני יודע *eini yodea* does not make it a problem. Very
straightforward answer. Okay. אמר להו *amar lehu*, he said to them, אי
הכי אמריתו בה טובא *ei hachi amritu bah tuva*. Oh, so you
know, so that's very important, you have said a... you know, that's
a very good insight. It's a pretty funny exchange, you know. Okay,
maybe I just benefit from having learned the גמרא *Gemara*, but it
does seem like the answer was pretty straightforward.
Anyway, but they were saying like what's my חידוש *chiddush*, it's an
obvious thing. He said, no no no, that's actually a very big
חידוש *chiddush* that you just said. אמריתו בה טובא *amritu bah tuva*,
you said a big... you said a big חידוש *chiddush*. אמרו ליה
*amru lei*, they said to him, מטיבותא דמר אמרינן בה *mitivusa d’mar
amrinan bah*. טובא טובא מנזיחותא דמר minizihuta d'mar, לא אמרינן בה ולא
חדא. lo amrinan bah v'lo chada,
Excuse me, I read that wrong. מניחותא דמר אמרינן בה טובא, minichuta
d'mar amrinan bah tuva,
you know, because you were so kind and generous and you said,
"No, tell me what you're learning, I'm curious" and whatever, because of
that, we responded similarly in a generous way and we shared our
תורה with you. מנזיחותא דמר, if you had been more, you know,
critical,
and you were like it was clear to us that you were
trying to, you know, not be generous but say like, "Oh, what
did רב פפא Rav Papa say?" like, on, and I, and you
were going to try to find fault with it and challenge it
because we know sometimes this enterprise can be somewhat competitive. So then
לא אמרינן בה ולא חדא, we wouldn't have said anything. Okay, so
it seems like they were testing him out and feeling him out
in the exchange to see is he trying to make trouble or
does he really and trying to find something to find fault or
does he really want to learn. And then they responded and they
said, "Oh, because it was clear you really wanted to learn and
you were being so generous, that's why we responded in a similarly
generous way." Okay, we will end here.